<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last sermon preached before his Maiesties funerals at Denmark house: on Tuesday the third of May. / By Phinees Hodson Dr of Diuinitie, one of his Maiesties chaplaines.</title>
            <author>Hodson, Phineas, d. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104134</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839873</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4332</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4332)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1242:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last sermon preached before his Maiesties funerals at Denmark house: on Tuesday the third of May. / By Phinees Hodson Dr of Diuinitie, one of his Maiesties chaplaines.</title>
                  <author>Hodson, Phineas, d. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M[iles] F[lesher] for Hannah Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4332:1"/>
            <p>THE LAST SERMON PREACHED BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE HIS MAIESTIES Funerals, at <hi>Denmark houſe: On Tueſday the third of May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY PHINEES HODSON D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Diuinitie, one of his Maieſties Chaplaines.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Hannah Barret,</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4332:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4332:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOS. 1.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Moſes my Seruant is dead; now therefore ariſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EE that might not ſee GOD in the <hi>fiery buſh,</hi> but he muſt <hi>put off</hi> his <hi>ſhooes, Exod.</hi> 3. might not <hi>ſee</hi> him as hee is, till hee had <hi>put off</hi> the ſinfull <hi>body</hi> of his <hi>fleſh, Coloſſ.</hi> 2. yea, and the <hi>fleſh</hi> of his <hi>body</hi> too, the apparell of his ſoule; his <hi>ſhooes</hi> muſt off then, becauſe the place where hee ſtood was <hi>holy ground.</hi> No maruell if his <hi>body</hi> muſt off now, before hee enter into the <hi>Sanctum Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.12. GOD told <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> that for their <hi>vnbeleefe</hi> they ſhould not <hi>bring</hi> the people into the <hi>Land</hi> which hee had promiſed them; and ſhortly after, euen at the next remoue from <hi>Cades</hi> to mount <hi>Hor, Aaron</hi> muſt vp to the mount, and there <hi>die. Moſes</hi> is repriued, till he come to the other ſide of <hi>Iordan,</hi> but not pardoned; and GOD will let
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4332:3"/> him <hi>ſee</hi> that Land, which he may not poſſeſſe. Nor is he therefore ſecure, he forgets not his ſummons, but finding himſelfe by account to be an hundred and twenty yeares old, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. and therefore hee could not liue long; that he was come to the ſide of that <hi>Riuer,</hi> which he might not paſſe; and therfore, in all likelihood, hee drew very neere, he prepares himſelfe to welcome the good will of GOD. When <hi>Moſes</hi> is readie, but not before, GOD calls again, and <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>Vp</hi> he muſt to mount <hi>Nebal,</hi> and there die. <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. Vp he goes, and when GOD had let him <hi>ſee the Land,</hi> he died, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. was buried, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and the reſt of the <hi>Chapter</hi> containes a Funerall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, made by <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in the commendation of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after <hi>Moſes'</hi> death and buriall, the <hi>LORD</hi> ſpake vnto <hi>Ioſhua</hi> (the <hi>verſe</hi> before my text, &amp; in my text) <hi>Moſes my ſeruant, &amp;c. Moſes is dead,</hi> buried by an <hi>Angel,</hi> mourned for by the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrically commended by <hi>Ioſhua:</hi> and that which he ſaid of him is recorded to poſterity, that all ages may know, that none is like to <hi>Moſes:</hi> Yet this is not enough, GOD vndertakes the matter himſelfe; for when an <hi>Angel</hi> beares the Coffin, and that by <hi>Gods</hi> owne appointment, and (for ought we know) made his Graue too: No wonder if the ſame GOD vouchſafe to reuiue his memory, and not ſo much as name <hi>Moſes</hi> without honourable mention, <hi>Moſes my ſeruant.</hi> Yea being dead, hee referres, and as it were appeales to <hi>Moſes; As I ſaid vnto Moſes,</hi> v. 3.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4332:3"/> and if he will comfort <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> hee <hi>will be with him as he was with Moſes, v.</hi> 5. for that will ſerue: yea hee cals his owne Law, <hi>the Law which Moſes my ſeruant commanded, v.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>And ſurely much was it, that a man, (but it was the man of GOD <hi>Moſes, Deu.</hi> 33.1.) that a man (I ſay) ſhould receiue ſuch teſtimonie from his Maker. But wel it was for them, whom he left behind him, well it was for <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> to whoſe charge they were left, &amp; little enough it was, that he that was the <hi>Seruant of the Lord</hi> in <hi>Gods</hi> mouth, ſhould be the <hi>ſeruant of the Lord</hi> in <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> mouth, <hi>v.</hi> 13. And if GOD will call his own Law <hi>Moſes' Law, Ioſhua</hi> would be bold to call <hi>Gods</hi> Land, <hi>Moſes'</hi> Land, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. And if GOD promiſed to be with <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> as hee was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> they will aske no more, they will pray for no more, but <hi>the Lord be with thee as hee was with Moſes.</hi> So then, well it was with <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> it got him authoritie; well it was with the <hi>people,</hi> it taught them obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for if GOD will be with <hi>Ioſhua</hi> as he was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> they will <hi>obey</hi> him as they did <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are deliuered by GOD to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and haue two parts; firſt, <hi>Gods</hi> teſtimony of <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, his Commiſsion to <hi>Ioſhua.</hi> The teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in theſe words, <hi>[Moſes my ſeruant is dead:]</hi> the Commiſsion, <hi>[Now therefore ariſe.]</hi> In the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony are two generall parts conſiderable; firſt, the <hi>Author,</hi> ſecondly, the <hi>Matter:</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet downe in the firſt <hi>verſe.</hi> Secondly, In the <hi>Matter</hi> are foure circumſtances; firſt, <hi>Servus,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4332:4"/> 
               <hi>Meus,</hi> thirdly, <hi>Moſes,</hi> fourthly, <hi>Mortuus.</hi> In the Commiſsion are two things; firſt, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, <hi>[Now therefore,]</hi> ſecondly, the tenor of the Commiſsion, <hi>[Ariſe.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Now therefore,]</hi> Not before thou receiue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till then lie ſtill, take not vpon thee; when I ſay the word, <hi>Ariſe.</hi> While hee liueth thou art his <hi>Miniſter, v.</hi> 1. and at his command, no <hi>riſing</hi> then without his direction: with his life his power cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>My people lacke an head, and I haue made choice of thee, [Now therefore, Ariſe.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To returne. The <hi>Author</hi> of this Declaratorie Commemoration and honourable recognition is GOD himſelfe: he commemorates him, for hee names <hi>Moſes,</hi> though <hi>dead;</hi> hee declares his worth, in calling him his <hi>Seruant.</hi> And a recognition it is, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> had done it before, GOD now againe, by a poſtliminious ſolemnization of his Funerals. Nor may it ſeeme ſtrange; <hi>Funerall Sermons</hi> are ordinarily made by ſuch as are neere to thoſe that are deceaſed, and haue ſome intereſt in their memories: then who ſhould rather doe this office to <hi>Moſes</hi> then his gratious <hi>Maſter?</hi> who had before teſtified of him, that he <hi>was faithfull in all his houſe, Numb.</hi> 12. Others heard GOD, <hi>Moſes heard,</hi> and <hi>ſaw him,</hi> and <hi>talked with him, as a man talkes with his friend, Exod.</hi> 33. yea, <hi>face</hi> to <hi>face, Deut.</hi> 34.10. Hence he continues to honor him dead, as he did aliue; liuing he was his <hi>ſeruant,</hi> and being dead, from <hi>Gods</hi> owne mouth, he receiues the ſame
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4332:4"/> teſtimony, <hi>Moſes my ſeruant is dead.</hi> For his perſon was not ordinary, <hi>There aroſe not a Prophet like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Moſes, Deut.</hi> 34.10. His <hi>Buriall</hi> was not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, other men had <hi>Sepulchers,</hi> as monuments of their mortality; <hi>Moſes</hi> had none, leſt his <hi>body</hi> ſhould haue beene <hi>abuſed to Idolatry.</hi> Others haue <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> to ſhew they haue beene; <hi>Moſes</hi> had none, leſt he ſhould haue beene thought that, which hee was not, and adored for a Diety. And more hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable it was for <hi>Moſes</hi> he had none, then for others, when they are moſt ſumptuous, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: <hi>Praefulgebant Iunius &amp; Blaeſus, eo ipſo, quod effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies eorum non viſebantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though it bee true, which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayes, that theſe ſolemnities at Funerals, are rather <hi>Solatia vivorum,</hi> then <hi>Subſidia mortuorum,</hi> yet whether we call it an act of civility, as from men to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; or an act of loue, to proſecute with honor thoſe that are dead, to whom we gaue reſpect, while they were liuing; or an act of neceſſitie, to free the liuing from the contagion of the dead; or an act of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to remoue their bodies from our ſight, and thereby ſorrow from our hearts; or an act tending to mortification, as being Remonſtrances of our frailty and mortality; or an act of hope, as implying their reſurrection, whom with ſo much care and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect we interre; or an act of faith and religion, as thereby teaching others, and leauing an impreſſion in our own hearts of our faith in him, that is our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection &amp; our life;</hi> whether any of theſe, or all, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4332:5"/> others that I conceiue not, moue <hi>Gods</hi> ſpirit, ſure it is, he commends the <hi>Buriall</hi> of the <hi>dead,</hi> as a godly and charitable worke, reports the circumſtances of perſons, place, pompe, care, coſt of embalming the bodies of the <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> of their paines in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting them to their owne <hi>Sepulchers;</hi> yea the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in the Goſpel are approued for their intended care to our <hi>Sauiours</hi> bodie. It is a bleſſing promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the <hi>godly,</hi> that they <hi>ſhall goe to their graue in peace,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. It is a curſe threatned to the <hi>wicked,</hi> that they ſhall want <hi>buriall,</hi> ſo of <hi>Iehoiakim, They ſhall not lament for him, nor ſay, Ah my brother! nor mourne for him, ſaying, Ah my Lord!</hi> or, <hi>Ah his glorie! but they ſhall burie him as an Aſſe, drawne and caſt forth beyond the gates of Ieruſalem. Ier.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>And though the place of <hi>Moſes buriall</hi> bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, that the <hi>Devill</hi> might not haue his <hi>body,</hi> yet the world ſhall haue his fame; and if <hi>Moſes die, All Iſrael</hi> ſhall <hi>mourne for him;</hi> an <hi>Angel</hi> ſhall burie him; <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſhall commend him; and if all this be not yet enough, GOD himſelfe ſhall giue him an honorable firname, that all poſterities may take notice of his loue to his <hi>Seruant Moſes.</hi> Thus much for the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> the <hi>LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Matter,</hi> I obſerued foure things, <hi>Servus, Meus, Moſes, Mortuus;</hi> for they riſe by degrees, and make ſeuerall parts. For firſt, that <hi>Servus</hi> ſhould be <hi>Mortuus,</hi> it is no maruell: but why <hi>Servus Meus</hi> ſhould die, may be enquired. And not only <hi>Servus Meus,</hi> but <hi>Servus Meus Moſes</hi> will make a further
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4332:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Quare.</hi> And it's <hi>Gods</hi> owne Rhetorique, who makes <hi>Moſes</hi> more than <hi>Servus Meus,</hi> when he ſaid to <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam, Wherefore were yee not afraid to ſpeake againſt my Seruant, euen againſt Moſes? Numb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Firſt then for <hi>Servus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Servi</hi> are <hi>Captivi, Emptitij,</hi> or <hi>Nativi;</hi> the laſt are ſuch as deſcend of the other two: and of all, One ſaid, <hi>Primos ſervos bella fecerunt;</hi> for when men were taken in warres, and <hi>jure belli occidi poſſent, quia ſervati Servi appellati.</hi> And hence likewiſe were they called <hi>Mancipia, quia manu capti.</hi> And of this another ſaith; <hi>Of all euils warre is the worſt; in warre, ſeruitude,</hi> whereby <hi>perſonae</hi> become <hi>res,</hi> other mens Chattels; which they doe as abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly command and diſpoſe of, as any thing they elſe poſſeſſe. We read of <hi>Vedius Pollio,</hi> who had many ſeruants, that cauſed one to be caſt into a <hi>Fiſh-pond for breaking a glaſse.</hi> Hence were <hi>ſeruants</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitare in mortalitate,</hi> to <hi>dwell in</hi> the very <hi>gates and ſhadow of death,</hi> becauſe they were ſlaine vpon euery trifling occaſion. Then that <hi>Servus</hi> ſhould be <hi>Mortuus</hi> is no maruell.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giues it another pettigree; <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum vel adverſitas, vel iniquitas fecit,</hi> Aduerſity made all the former <hi>Seruants;</hi> Iniquity made <hi>Cham</hi> a <hi>ſeruant.</hi> Now we commiſerate thoſe which are made <hi>ſeruants</hi> by aduerſity; wee abhorre <hi>Cham,</hi> made a <hi>ſeruant</hi> by iniquitie, and we our ſelues are in the ſame eſtate, and yet are ſecure. All our liues,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4332:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and liberties were made forfeit in <hi>Adam,</hi> and by his tranſgreſſion wee became <hi>ſlaues to ſinne, death,</hi> and the <hi>Diuell.</hi> Herein <hi>Servus</hi> and <hi>Mortuus</hi> ſo well agree, that vnleſſe wee had beene <hi>ſeruants to ſinne, Death</hi> had not beene <hi>Lord ouer vs;</hi> for, <hi>Mors non acceſsiſſet, niſi culpa praeceſsiſſet. Sinner</hi> and <hi>Slaue</hi> are now become <hi>Termini convertibiles: To whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you giue your ſelues ſeruants to obey, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant you are, to whom you obey. Rom.</hi> 6. And the conſequence of that <hi>ſeruice</hi> is <hi>death;</hi> ſo it there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>whether it be of ſinne vnto death.</hi> Yea the ſame Apoſtle more directly; <hi>By one man ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo ſinne raigned ouer all, Rom.</hi> 5. Then <hi>Servus</hi> muſt die, and <hi>Servus</hi> and <hi>Mortuus</hi> doe ſo agree, that they cannot bee parted. But if <hi>Servus</hi> and <hi>Mortuus</hi> agree, may not <hi>Servus Meus</hi> be priuiledged? Let vs examine <hi>Meus,</hi> ſo ſhall wee ſee how <hi>Mortuus</hi> doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge.</p>
            <p>In a large ſenſe <hi>Servi Dei,</hi> or <hi>Servi mei,</hi> are <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nei, Transfuga, Domeſtici;</hi> &amp; all theſe three he <hi>feeds</hi> as he doth the <hi>Ravens; cloathes</hi> as he doth the <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies;</hi> ſhowers downe his bleſſings vpon them with an indifferent, or rather vnequall proportion: Many times ſuffering the firſt two to ſwimme in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, whileſt his owne <hi>Domeſtici</hi> are buſie in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding neceſſaries. Where's the priuiledge then of <hi>Servus Meus? Much euery way,</hi> for though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity and miſery break in like <hi>Rivers,</hi> to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of all man-kinde, the firſt of Iniquitie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4332:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the <hi>Divell,</hi> the ſecond of Miſery, by the firſt of iniquitie; whereby it's true of all mankinde, <hi>Servum vel iniquitas, vel aduerſitas fecit:</hi> yet here's the difference betweene <hi>Servus,</hi> and <hi>Servus Meus,</hi> we were all by the <hi>Woman</hi> made <hi>ſeruants,</hi> but there's another <hi>Seed</hi> that ouercame the <hi>Devill;</hi> the <hi>Woman,</hi> conquered, loſt vs all; but the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the <hi>Woman</hi> by a new onſet preuailed, and <hi>jure belli</hi> freed vs from that <hi>ſlauerie,</hi> wherein hee found vs; and of <hi>vaſſals to ſinne,</hi> made vs <hi>ſeruants</hi> to himſelfe. And this he did by a <hi>mighty hand,</hi> whereby we are now made <hi>Mancipia</hi> to our <hi>Redeemer.</hi> The firſt two are <hi>ſervi,</hi> but onely <hi>Poteſtatis,</hi> and ſo are the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills;</hi> the laſt <hi>Domeſtici,</hi> are <hi>Servi gratiae.</hi> Now the queſtion is not of the two former, but what ſhall become of <hi>Domeſtici.</hi> Shall <hi>Servi gratiae</hi> die too? Yes, <hi>Chriſts</hi> victorie freed vs from the <hi>ſecond death,</hi> the <hi>Curſe of the Law;</hi> not from the firſt, the <hi>effects of ſinne.</hi> Nor is it therefore a ſmall bleſſing to bee <hi>Servus Dei,</hi> it was a part of that bleſſing, (as ſome Divines doe expound it) which <hi>Iſaac</hi> gaue to <hi>Eſau, Servies fratri, Gen.</hi> 27.40. Then what a ſtay, what an honour, what a comfort hath <hi>Servus meus?</hi> that is, <hi>ſeruant to the moſt High. Pſal.</hi> 119. If once we can come to this, to get our ſelues booked in this <hi>Checke-roll,</hi> ſuch a man while hee liues <hi>ſhall want no manner of thing that is good, Pſ.</hi> 34. that's for this life; and in the end he ſhall haue a reward, yea, an <hi>Exceeding great reward,</hi> as GOD promiſed to <hi>Abraham:</hi> for how ſhould he forget his owne <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4332:7"/>
            <p>It's ſayd that GOD loues <hi>Adverbes</hi> in men bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>Adjectiues;</hi> Man, ſure, loues this <hi>Pronoune poſſeſsiue,</hi> better than any other <hi>part of Speech:</hi> there being no good thing in this world, whereto hee would not haue <hi>Meum</hi> ioyn'd. Oh that hee would bee as carefull to get poſſeſſion of GOD, that with confidence wee could ſay vnto him, <hi>Deus meus!</hi> For if this reciprocall bond were once paſt, that wee could ſay to him, <hi>Deus meus,</hi> and hee to vs, <hi>Servi mei,</hi> it ſhould neuer bee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled; once <hi>His,</hi> and alwayes <hi>His,</hi> liuing and dead hee neuer forſakes vs; <hi>My ſheepe ſhall none plucke out of my hands, Iohn</hi> 10.28. Here on earth wee ſometimes loſe our <hi>Seruices,</hi> ſometimes our <hi>Lords and Maſters,</hi> but <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit Deo,</hi> his tenure holds throughout all Generations. Its true, Nor <hi>Servus Meus,</hi> nor <hi>Amicus noſter</hi> will ſerue for <hi>Priviledge</hi> in the caſe of death, but <hi>Servus Meus Mortuus, Amicus noſter dormit:</hi> onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, if <hi>Servus Meus,</hi> and <hi>Amicus noster,</hi> and hee whom <hi>Chriſt loued</hi> bee dead, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.3. why ſhould any man bee afraid? If death were a Scorpion, <hi>Servus Meus,</hi> and <hi>Amicus noster</hi> ſhould not bee endangered by it: then let <hi>ſinne raigne to death,</hi> ſo <hi>Grace</hi> alſo <hi>raigne vnto righteouſneſſe, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus Chriſt vnto eternall life, Rom.</hi> 5. So then, nor <hi>Servus,</hi> nor <hi>Servus Meus</hi> exclude <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if <hi>Death</hi> bee not afraid, like <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam,</hi> to ſet vpon <hi>my Seruant,</hi> dare it aduenture
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4332:7"/> vpon <hi>Moſes;</hi> may not hee bee priuiledged? whoſe life was a booke not of <hi>Lamentations, and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and woes, Ezek.</hi> 2. (though euen of theſe it had reaſonable ſtore of marginall notes) but a booke of <hi>Priuiledges</hi> and <hi>Miracles,</hi> and ſtrange ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, ſuch as (ſet him aſide) the world neuer had among the <hi>Sons of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Begin at his birth. In the <hi>Edict</hi> againſt the male Children hee was priuiledged and preſerued from death: When <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſought his life, for ſlaying the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> then was hee likewiſe priuiledged, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. yea in thoſe <hi>Wonders,</hi> which hee wrought in <hi>Pharaohs Court,</hi> hee was ſo priuiledged, that the wrath <hi>of the King</hi> was not onely no <hi>meſſenger of death,</hi> but he did fawne vpon <hi>Moſes,</hi> as if he would licke the duſt of his feet; <hi>I haue ſinned againſt</hi> GOD, <hi>and againſt you, and I pray you forgiue mee this once, Exod.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Aaron</hi> was great, yet was <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>God, Exod.</hi> 4. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was a great <hi>King,</hi> yet was <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>God,</hi> too; <hi>Exod.</hi> 7. And as <hi>God,</hi> hee not onely receiued, but gaue priuiledges. Was it not a great priuiledge that hee gaue vnto the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that they ſhould not wet their feet, where <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was drown'd and all his hoaſt? <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. No maruell, if hee made the <hi>Sea</hi> a <hi>Wall</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that drew <hi>water out of the Rocke</hi> for the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> The <hi>Sea,</hi> nothing more fluid; the <hi>Rocke,</hi> nothing more hard; and the <hi>Rocke</hi> againe a <hi>Riuer:</hi> that ſtill <hi>Moſes</hi> life was a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of priuiledges. Nor was his Power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4332:8"/> to the Earth, or Sea, it reached to Heauen, where it brought downe <hi>Manna,</hi> for their <hi>bread,</hi> and <hi>Quailes</hi> for their <hi>food.</hi> And may not this Man of priuiledges bee priuiledged to goe ſome other way; but by the gates of death, euen <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt paſſe to life? Hee that had beene ſo long entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Angels</hi> food in the Mount, that when hee came downe <hi>his face did ſhine,</hi> as if hee had beene transfigured, ſo as <hi>they were afraid to looke vpon him;</hi> may not He bee tranſlated to heauen, <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> together, but that skinne, once ſo bright muſt bee eaten with wormes? GOD intreated <hi>Moſes, Let mee alone,</hi> (as if without his leaue hee could doe nothing) <hi>that I may conſume them;</hi> hee offers him faire conditious, ſo indulgent was GOD to <hi>Moſes,</hi> that hee would buy his conſent, <hi>Let mee conſume them, and I will make of thee a mighty peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Exod.</hi> 32.10. And <hi>Moſes</hi> preuailed with GOD, but GOD could not preuaile with <hi>Moſes,</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed, and chid, <hi>verſe</hi> 11, <hi>Why doth the wrath of my Lord waxe hot againſt his people?</hi> And pleads, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. <hi>Leſt the Aegyptians ſay, hee brought them malitiouſly out of Aegypt to deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Yea in the ſame <hi>verſe</hi> hee importunes GOD yet further; <hi>Turne from thy fierce wrath:</hi> nay chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges GOD of his word, <hi>verſe</hi> 13. <hi>Remember A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> yea charges him with his oath, <hi>which thou ſwareſt vnto them:</hi> Then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this, the <hi>Lord changed his minde from the euill he meant to bring vpon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4332:8"/>
            <p>You ſee his <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and you ſee his power, but neuer a word on <hi>Gods</hi> part, that he ſhall not die; neuer a word on his owne part that hee may not die. Hee that would not <hi>let</hi> GOD <hi>alone</hi> for his people, lets him alone for himſelfe; neuer opens his mouth; but hearing of death, as a thing that neuer troubled him, hee addreſſeth himſelfe to diſpatch ſuch buſineſſe as was fit for a man of his qualitie and place. And being ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the world, hee <hi>bleſſed the people, went vp to the mount,</hi> and there hee <hi>dyed.</hi> I ſaid before, if <hi>Seruus Meus</hi> dye, why ſhould any man feare? Now if <hi>Moſes</hi> bee dead, none ſhall eſcape. One example we haue before the Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. <hi>Enoch was taken away, and was no more ſeene:</hi> and the ſame GOD, that diſpenſed with one before, priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged one other in the time of the <hi>Law,</hi> but long after, in the times of <hi>Iehoram</hi> King of <hi>Iuda, Elijah in a whirewinde was caried vp to Heauen,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2. GOD vouchſafing to thoſe ſeuerall ages of the world, demonſtrations of our immortality But this was extraordinarie; two there were, and but two, to ſhew that wee are bound, and hee is not, but hath a tranſcendent power ouer all the <hi>workes of his hands.</hi> Nor was hee frequent in making ſuch grants, leſt any man ſhould challenge; and thoſe rather to <hi>good,</hi> than to <hi>great men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though in <hi>Elijahs</hi> time, when devotion grew cold, fifty ſonnes of the Prophets were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to bee witneſſes, it was not yeelded to in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4332:9"/> 
               <hi>Enoch's</hi> time, none were then ſuffered to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; yea, it is deliuered in obſcure tearmes; <hi>Enoch</hi> was <hi>taken away,</hi> not <hi>taken vp,</hi> ſo wary was GOD in paſſing ſuch grants.</p>
            <p>The beſt then muſt die; <hi>Servus meus,</hi> and <hi>Amicus noster,</hi> GODS <hi>ſeruants,</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> all are dead, and the greateſt cannot eſcape. For if <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo great, and (beſides all ye haue heard) ſo honored, that many ages after, GOD reviueth his memory, and ſaith, <hi>Though Moſes ſtood before mee, I would not bee intreated, Ier.</hi> 15.1. If <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo famous to poſterity, and whoſe memory is ſo frequent in the Scriptures, that it is mentioned aboue an hundred and twenty times in the old Teſtament after his death, and almoſt as often in the new, and that by many honourable teſtimonies euen from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, if hee might not be ſpared; let all generations ſubmit themſelues to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which the beſt and greateſt haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone. Then let not ſtrength preſume, hee whoſe <hi>eye</hi> was not <hi>dimme,</hi> nor <hi>naturall force abated,</hi> when hee was <hi>an hundred and twenty yeeres old,</hi> is dead, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. Let not courage: he that ſo brauely ſlew the <hi>Egyptian</hi> in the defence of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is himſelfe dead: Let not beauty; the <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Countenance</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7.) is now become duſt and aſhes. Let not power magnifie it ſelfe; hee that deſtroyed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, euen <hi>Moſes</hi> is laid downe, and cannot riſe vp. Let not wiſdome and learning boaſt; his thoughts
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4332:9"/> are periſhed, that was learned in <hi>all the knowledge of the Aegyptians, Acts</hi> 7. Let not authority and pre-eminence, <hi>Pharaohs God,</hi> and <hi>Aarons God,</hi> a man greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Pope</hi> wold be thought to be, aboue <hi>Prince,</hi> aboue <hi>Prieſt,</hi> is now diſſolued into duſt. Let not the fauor of the multitude, they can <hi>mourn thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes for Moſes'</hi> death, they cannot fetch him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, once dead. In a word, ſuppoſe a man's <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> and <hi>priviledges</hi> be neuer ſo many ſo as his life ſeem a continued miracle, a miraculous Funerall he may haue, but he muſt die, for <hi>Moſes is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if preſent examples moue more, <hi>King IAMES</hi> is dead too, in whom many of theſe priuiledges met, and a number of other excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which diuided giue honour to others: euen <hi>Gods</hi> ſeruant <hi>Moſes,</hi> and our late Soueraigne <hi>King IAMES,</hi> both are dead. Then what may this <hi>Mortuus</hi> be that thus incroacheth?</p>
            <p>There is a threefold death, a death by ſin, a death to ſin, and a death for ſin. The firſt is the death of the Soule: the ſecond, the death of ſin in the ſoule; the third is the parting of the body and ſoule. The firſt is alwaies euill, the ſecond alwayes good; the third is ſomtimes euill, ſometimes good, according to the quality of him whom it doth ſurpriſe. The firſt that cannot be good, and the laſt which may be euill, are both repayred by the ſecond, which is euer good and not euill. The firſt is <hi>deſerente Deo,</hi> when <hi>God forſakes</hi> a man's ſoule: the ſecond <hi>ſubveniente gratiâ,</hi> when <hi>Gods grace</hi> ſuſtaines a mans ſoule;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4332:10"/> the third is <hi>recedente animâ,</hi> when the body is forſaken by the ſoule. The firſt is the cauſe of the laſt; for, <hi>Mors mortem anteceſsit, voluntaria ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſariam:</hi> One death vſhered forth another; the voluntarie death of ſinne, the neceſſary death of the body. And this third is here meant, when hee ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> is dead. <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid of death, that it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>a looſing and ſeparating of the ſoule from the body.</hi> Two friends haue long liued together, and now they muſt part, and goe ſeuerall wayes, the one to earth, the other to heauen: For wee are not deſtroyed by death, but diſſolued to bee elſe-where placed. And this is cleare in this Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi> death; <hi>Thou ſhalt die</hi> (ſaith God) and <hi>ſleepe with thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Deut.</hi> 31.16. And, <hi>Thou ſhalt bee gathered to thy people, Deut.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>So that death is our <hi>ſleepe,</hi> and <hi>reſtitution</hi> to that place from whence wee deſcended. For when the ſoule leaues the body, GOD then gathers vs as ripe Corne into his Barne. And theſe conſiderations, that <hi>by death wee ſleepe with our Fathers,</hi> and <hi>are gathered to the Saints,</hi> as they did prepare him, ſo ſhould they ſatisfie vs, as carying in them ſecret reaſons, and conſolations againſt the terrours of death. So as now it is no ſtrange thing, that <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Meus,</hi> and <hi>Servus Meus Moſes</hi> ſhould dye, who thereby <hi>ſleepeth,</hi> and is <hi>gathered to his people. Iuſt Simeon</hi> looked vpon death, and eſteemed it, <hi>Nunc Dimittis: quaſi neceſsitate teneretur in hac
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4332:10"/> vitâ, non voluntate.</hi> Indeed death ſeemes not ſo to all, but that is not death's fault: for, <hi>Mors aut ſuae quietis bono vtitur, aut malo alieno labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> The reaſon is, <hi>Mors mala non eſt, niſi vbi vita mala.</hi> Yea to ſuch it is better to dye than to liue. It may ſeeme a Paradox, but it is none: for, <hi>quò vita diuturnior, culpa numeroſior:</hi> and therefore to that comfort, which <hi>Seneca</hi> giues againſt death, <hi>Deſinam aegrotare poſse, alligari, &amp;c. I ſhall no more be ſicke, no more impriſoned, no more tormented;</hi> wee may adde this as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, <hi>Deſinam peccare poſſe: I ſhall no more ſinne.</hi> And it is no ſmall aduantage to be freed from <hi>Sinning.</hi> It troubled S. <hi>Paul, Wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death, Rom.</hi> 7.24. where you ſee the Apoſtle as much troubled, that hee muſt liue, as others are, when they muſt dye. For, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerues, ſome that would liue, yet <hi>cùm patientiâ mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur;</hi> ſo others would dye, but <hi>cum patientiâ vivunt.</hi> For, <hi>Anima abſolvitur, corpus reſolvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; quae abſolvitur gaudet, quod reſolvitur nihil ſentit.</hi> So that this is one comfort, wee haue by the <hi>ſleepe of death;</hi> we reſt from ſinne, wee reſt from ſorrow.</p>
            <p>But this is not all: Hee that lyeth downe to ſleepe, makes account to awake; <hi>Vt cùm dormientes audimus evigilaturos, minimè deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus.</hi> For as it is true, that <hi>per vitam fit ad mortem tranſitus;</hi> ſo, <hi>per mortem fit ad vitam
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4332:11"/> reditus.</hi> Then let vs not be diſmayed with the maske and vizard of death, but rather joy, and comfort our ſelues, in ſo happy a paſſage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life. <hi>Bona vita, abſoluto certamine:</hi> that is the life we ſhould looke after; wherein the <hi>law of our members rebelleth</hi> no more <hi>againſt the law of our minde:</hi> where we ſhall haue no more ſtrife with this <hi>body of death,</hi> but ſhall haue <hi>victory</hi> ouer it. Thus <hi>ſlept</hi> and <hi>reſted Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> when hee was <hi>gathered to his people.</hi> For while wee are in this world, wee are ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp and downe as <hi>Pilgrims and ſtrangers,</hi> death brings vs <hi>home.</hi> Wee reade of <hi>Socrates</hi> that hee thirſted after death, that hee might meet with thoſe braue ſpirits, <hi>Orpheus</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod,</hi> and <hi>Homer:</hi> let not vs be weake and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolute, that ſhall bee <hi>gathered</hi> to the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> troopes of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> and <hi>Confeſsors,</hi> yea <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, in his fleſh, in his glory, <hi>ſitting at the right hand of God.</hi> It is true, to fleſh and blood, the ſhell of death ſeemes hard; but to him that hath the ſpirituall reliſh of the Apoſtle, it containes a ſweet kernell. How ſhall wee doe then to get S. <hi>Pauls</hi> taſte? there is but one way, and that is to keepe S. <hi>Pauls</hi> dyet, by accuſtoming our ſelues to <hi>dye daily,</hi> and <hi>by bearing about in our bodies the death of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. For then the <hi>life of the Lord Ieſus</hi> ſhould bee <hi>made manifeſt in our mortall fleſh.</hi> If thus wee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4332:11"/> could frame our ſelues to welcome death, <hi>adeò mors non eſſet timenda, vt ejus beneficio nihil ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then it is well with <hi>Moſes;</hi> happy is hee that euer hee was borne, to dye in ſuch a caſe. What ſhall become of the people? who ſhall <hi>goe in and out</hi> before them? they are as <hi>ſheepe without a ſhepheard,</hi> who ſhall gather them, that they may heare and learne, and feare, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the <hi>Commandements</hi> of GOD, and <hi>keepe the Law of the Lord, Deut.</hi> 31.12. <hi>Moſes</hi> is gone: who ſhall <hi>ſmite the rocke,</hi> that the people may drinke? who ſhall <hi>bring downe Manna</hi> for them, when they are hungry? who ſhall now <hi>hold vp his hands,</hi> that they may preuaile againſt their enemies? nay, when the people ſhall haue made GOD himſelfe their enemy, who ſhall <hi>ſtand in the gap</hi> betwixt GOD and them? or if they be at peace with GOD, who ſhall <hi>ſit in iudgement to make peace</hi> among them <hi>from the morning to the euening? Exod.</hi> 18. <hi>Moſes</hi> loued the people of GOD better then his owne ſoule, <hi>Spare them, or raſe me out of thy booke.</hi> Who ſhall care for them now? <hi>Moſes</hi> offered his <hi>ſoule</hi> for their <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> who will now offer his body for their ſoules?</p>
            <p>Yes, the ſame GOD that preſerued <hi>Moſes</hi> till hee came to the <hi>other ſide of Iordan,</hi> prouideth <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to bring them into the Land: for <hi>hee loueth his with an euerlaſting loue, Ier.</hi> 31. No
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4332:12"/> ſooner <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt dye, but <hi>Ioſua</hi> muſt <hi>ariſe:</hi> yea hee prepareth before-hand, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall not heare of death, till <hi>Ioſua</hi> be ready to take the charge: hee muſt prepare before-hand, but he muſt not take poſſeſſion, till <hi>Moſes</hi> be dead. Yea hee receiued this due commendation, <hi>Moſes my ſeruant,</hi> which was not onely an honor to <hi>Moſes,</hi> but an incouragement to <hi>Ioſua:</hi> for if hee doe as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, hee ſhall haue the honor which <hi>Moſes</hi> had.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay <hi>a greater than Moſes</hi> is lately dead amongſt vs, though euen for that purpoſe much might be ſaid: for ſtrip <hi>Moſes</hi> of his <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges</hi> and <hi>Extraordinaries,</hi> and though hee commanded much people and a great Army, yet had he no kingdome but a Wilderneſſe, that I know. That way <hi>King IAMES</hi> was greater than <hi>Moſes.</hi> Thus farre we may be bold. None was like <hi>Moſes</hi> among the <hi>Prophets;</hi> none like <hi>King Iames</hi> among the <hi>Kings. Moſes</hi> his priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges were many and great; <hi>King Iames</hi> his priuiledges not few, nor ſmall. None more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly preſerued than <hi>Moſes;</hi> none more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly preſerued than <hi>King Iames.</hi> And if <hi>Moſes</hi> were a great <hi>Warrior; King Iames</hi> was as great a <hi>Peace-maker.</hi> I would I had not cauſe to complaine, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> neuer murmured more againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> for bringing them out of their <hi>thraldome of Aegypt,</hi> then Many of vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſty for labouring to keepe the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4332:12"/> Drum and Cannon from amongſt vs. And though it be the duty of good Subiects, with <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Iapheth,</hi> ſo to couer their Soueraignes infirmities, as not to looke vpon them them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, yet hath it euer beene the condition of the beſt Princes, euen to bee traduced for their vertues. <hi>Vnum crimen conſiteor, Pacificus erat.</hi> Doubtleſſe for wiſedome and learning <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>King Iames</hi> were both admirable. What the <hi>learning of the Egyptians was,</hi> I diſpute not; but ſurely all ages will confeſſe and wonder at the learning of <hi>King Iames:</hi> a <hi>walking Library</hi> hee was, an abſtract of knowledge, an Oracle to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue Quaeſtions and Myſteries, the mirrour of this, and miracle of the next age; to which his abilities will ſeeme fabulous. All this hee had, and a <hi>large heart,</hi> and a large hand, and three great Kingdomes to attend his bounty, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it, but yet came ſhort of it: yet all this was ſo tempered, as it could not puffe him vp, nor make him proud, and herein hee was <hi>Meeke</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> was. And though I doubt not but he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued well to bee a King, and being carefull and jealous enough of his Prerogatiue, yet was hee euer beſt pleaſed, when hee was moſt like a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man. It was not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ght, that the <hi>Deuill</hi> in his temptation to our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> offered not onely <hi>all the kingdomes of the earth,</hi> but <hi>the glory of them:</hi> his Maieſty tooke his right to his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the glory of them</hi> he did not regard.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4332:13"/>
            <p>This was much, and yet but little, to that Crowne of his Crowne, his reſolution for <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and care of the <hi>Church,</hi> wherein hee repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented <hi>Moſes his Zeale.</hi> For his Reſolution to religion, Conſider his frequent <hi>Speeches</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely and priuately, his learned <hi>Writings,</hi> which ſhall liue with the world; his continuall exerciſe and attendance vpon the duties of Religion: And this I am perſwaded, that in two and twenty years (whiles he raigned ouer vs) he heard more Sermons, than all the Princes before him in two hundred. But if any malitiouſly ſhall impute this to a formality, or the outward obligation of his Vow, whereby hee had tyed himſelfe to thoſe weekely Exerciſes, for his preſeruation from the <hi>Traiterous Conſpiracy,</hi> (though euen the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous performance of ſuch vowes be not ordinary among <hi>Princes</hi>) I appeale to all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: Firſt for <hi>England,</hi> neuer Prince more carefull for the <hi>Church,</hi> neuer <hi>King</hi> more indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to the <hi>Clergy:</hi> if no more, ſo many <hi>Biſhops priuy Councellors,</hi> in an age, when ſuch honours and fauours were out of dare, doe ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it. If he had not laid the loue of religion neare his heart, he would not haue placed the <hi>Prelats,</hi> and Profeſſor of it ſo neere his perſon.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> wee ſhall ſpeake mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, but ſo much by mee more worthy to bee remembred, as they are by moſt men little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: in theſe, I ſay, hee reſtored <hi>one Church,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4332:13"/> and in effect new planted another; hee reſtored <hi>Scotland,</hi> and how did he this? by wreſting from the poſſeſſours ſuch titles as they had gotten to their reuennues? no, but by reſtitution of what the Crowne had gotten; by purchaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption vpon valuable conſideration, out of his owne coffers, he reſtored and ſetled the <hi>torne Church of Scotland:</hi> ſo as now it beareth the goodly face of a <hi>glorious Church.</hi> And by new indowments, where the old could not bee reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, hee founded many both <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We talke of the charity of former ages, but let our Aduerſaries bee ſilent and lay their hand vpon their mouth; I dare ſay (and I thinke I am not miſtaken) <hi>King IAMES</hi> hath teſtifyed his deuotion to the <hi>Church</hi> and Religion by more bounty &amp; charge, than the ſuperſtition of any ſix Kings together ſince the Conqueſt haue broght vpon them. So many <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> and <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo many in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all raiſed out of his owne Coffers and inheritance, if the value were caſt vp, (which I wiſh might be done, for the Kings eternall honour) would grow to ſuch a ſumme, as report would hardly find credit. Then if a <hi>Tree may be knowne by his fruits,</hi> by theſe take knowledge of his Maieſties loue to <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet is he <hi>dead,</hi> hee might not bee priuiledged in this point no more than <hi>Moſes;</hi> but this is our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4332:14"/> comfort and aſſurance, that GOD, would not bee wanting to ſo excellent an inſtrument of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, but to whom hee gaue graces, for the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and benefit of his Church, him he did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with all ſuch graces as were neceſſary to the ſaluation of his owne ſoule; and then <hi>death was his advantage: Regnum Dei intra nos est.</hi> Vpon which words St. <hi>Hierom</hi> notes, that <hi>As a man that is free of any City, trauell where he wil through the world, hee is ſtill a Citizen and free of that place,</hi> ſo if we can once truly ſay, <hi>Regnum Dei intra nos eſt,</hi> though we walke on earth, <hi>Habemus municipatum in coelis.</hi> And then ſuppoſe, his late Maieſty loſt not <hi>three Kingdoms,</hi> but thirty three Kingdomes, they are all well exchanged for <hi>One Kingdome in Heauen.</hi> Nor haue wee cauſe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to cry out with Saint <hi>Hierom,</hi> vpon the death of <hi>Nepotian, Cui jam meum ſudabit inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium? cui literulae placere gestient? quicquid dixero, quia ille non audit, mutum videtur.</hi> For though he be dead <hi>Ioſhua</hi> is aliue, the moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>ſonne</hi> of an incomparable <hi>Father;</hi> and happy we, ſeeing GOD hath taken ſuch a <hi>Moſes</hi> from vs, that he hath prouided ſuch a <hi>Ioſua</hi> for vs.</p>
            <p>And obſerue now therefore: for if <hi>Moſes</hi> death enabled <hi>Ioſua,</hi> he muſt not ſtir till hee dye, nay hee muſt attend <hi>Moſes death</hi> and <hi>Gods call;</hi> for ſo it was neceſſary, where there was no ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: but where the ſucceſſion of a Kingdome is eſtabliſhed in a line, the death of the <hi>Father</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4332:14"/> calls the <hi>ſonne;</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thereby GOD ſpeakes to him as if in expreſſe tearmes he called, <hi>Ariſe.</hi> The laſt breath of the Predeceſſour giueth firſt title and poſſeſſion to the Succeſſor; and though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo faint when it goes out, it cryeth aloud, <hi>Ariſe.</hi> Herein let vs magnifie <hi>Gods Providence</hi> for our <hi>Ioſua,</hi> that as he preſerued <hi>Moſes</hi> till <hi>Ioſua</hi> was ready; ſo did he preſerue our <hi>Moſes</hi> till our <hi>Ioſua</hi> was fit; ſo fit, and ſo incomparably worthy, as if ſucceſſion did not caſt the Kingdome vpon him: vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> elſe ſhould we affixe our eies &amp; harts? where ſhould we chooſe ſuch another? we haue read of ſome that haue been ſo compoſed, as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes virtutes,</hi> and <hi>ingentia vitia</hi> did ſtriue whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould exceed: but ſo much vertue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exception, where ſhall wee finde? <hi>Non ſemper errat Fatum, aliquando eligit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that our gracious <hi>King</hi> comes to vs in the parallel of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> I conceiue hope, and I cannot but conceiue it, that hee will likewiſe come to vs in the <hi>Power of Ioſua:</hi> The greateſt act of <hi>Ioſuah's</hi> power appeared in this, that at his word the <hi>Sunne and Moone ſtood ſtill till hee was auenged on his enemies.</hi> Amongſt the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> wee find that they make the <hi>Pope the Sunne,</hi> and the <hi>Emperor the Moone;</hi> this they, to magnifie the <hi>Pope</hi> ſo many degrees aboue the <hi>Emperor,</hi> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> exceedes the <hi>Moone.</hi> But the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>Moone</hi> they muſt be, &amp; ſo let them be; prouided, that at the mighty
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4332:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>power of our Ioſua,</hi> and his wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Sun</hi> &amp; <hi>Moone ſtand ſtill,</hi> or be not able to <hi>goe forward one degree,</hi> till hee bee auenged of the <hi>blood of</hi> thoſe <hi>Saints,</hi> which hath beene ſo prodigally ſhed; and till <hi>Thoſe</hi> of his owne <hi>Royall blood</hi> be deliuered from the oppreſſions, which now they ſuffer, and bee reſtored to thoſe <hi>Inheritances</hi> and honors, which haue ſo violently beene torne from them.</p>
            <p>Now therefore <hi>Ariſe,</hi> yea let <hi>our Ioſua ariſe,</hi> like the morning Sunne, and thruſt the vſurper out of his ſeat. Let him <hi>Ariſe,</hi> and <hi>let his enemies be ſcattered;</hi> but <hi>let his throne bee eſtabliſhed from generation to generation:</hi> let the hand of <hi>God</hi> be eſtabliſhed with him, and let his arme ſtrengthen him: but <hi>Lord deſtroy his foes before his face, and plague thoſe that hate him.</hi> Let thy <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> euer be with him, and in thy name <hi>let his power be exalted:</hi> Make him thy <hi>firſt borne, higher than the Kings of the earth:</hi> make <hi>his ſeed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for euer, and his throne as the dayes of heauen!</hi> And let all the people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped, in ſome Copies.</head>
            <p>PAg. <hi>3.</hi> Lin. <hi>13. reade</hi> Ioſhua will be, &amp;c. Pag. <hi>11.</hi> lin. <hi>22. dele</hi> him. Pag. <hi>13.</hi> lin. <hi>21. reade</hi> Immortalitie, Pag. <hi>15.</hi> lin. <hi>7. reade</hi> — for Moſes death, they cannot fetch him againe, once dead. Pag. <hi>16.</hi> lin. penult. <hi>reade</hi> Thus Simeon.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
